Leah: As we have already discussed previously
choosing the right deployment strategy for a
project would include several considerations.
One serious consideration is
it’s support with rollback.
Chris: Rollback is the process of ‘rolling
back’ a software product to a previous version.
This normally occurs when there is an issue
with the current release [the latest version]
such as several bug fixes that need to be done.
It may be a simple process if it only involves
small changes: However, it could become an issue
if it involves several elements of a software
project, as they may have multiple dependencies.
It would also become an issue, if the deployment
strategy choice, such as Basic deployment,
makes it difficult to support rollback.
Leah: Rollbacks can be fully automated,
this is where a system would examine
a set measurement or metric, and would
either, mark it as complete which would
finish the deployment, or roll it back.
Rollbacks need to be quick, so as not to
interrupt the end user using the product,
and if the product uses a database, it
will need to ensure that no data is lost.
Chris: For deployments to be successful,
a rollback strategy would need to be
considered in the Deployment plan.
This written document outlines all the
steps required to recover an application
and or database to the point before the
deployment, outlining the specific steps
for each member of the deployment team.
The plan would be tested so all the
components could be determined, and it
would include the locations of the scripts,
needed to ‘rollback’ the deployment.
It would also include the database name and the
developer responsible for running the scripts.
Leah: When something does go wrong with
a deployment, a team is more likely
to respond in a systematic, calm, and
logical way if it has a rollback strategy.